soft engineering radio episode 131
interview with Tom DeMarco and Peter
whose car this is software engineering
radio the podcast for professional
developers on the web at se - radio
dotnet
my radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
hello welcome to another episode of
software engineering radio this is the
second episode that has been recorded as
a joint a/c radio and Hopi session
obviously at over P 2009 the first one
was the pros amps discussion on security
a couple of weeks ago this discussion is
with Tom DeMarco and Peter ooshka about
their new book adrenaline junkies
actually that's the book is co-authored
by all the members of the Atlantic
systems guild but those two guys were
and they will pee and and then talked
about what the book was all about we
conducted the session as a live
interview on stage so there are a couple
of audience questions after the show Tom
told me that he that he liked the format
and they did that he would like to do it
again at some point so I'm sure at some
point we'll have Tom DeMarco back maybe
talking about some of his legendary
earlier work as last time we want to
once again thank the organizers of the
Opie conference that's six datacom and
Francis polished a program chair for
taking the risk and trying this su radio
life thing on stage and well I guess
there were no big complaints and again
I'm looking forward to your feedback
what you think about it as the offline
audience now in the podcast
okay that's all for the preliminaries
let's get on with the interview have fun
okay welcome everybody very loud to this
joint session between the Opie and
software engineering radio the podcast
might have heard about it so this
session is is recorded and then
broadcast in the podcast later on that's
also why we do it as a discussion as an
interview and before we so the last
third of the session is intended for you
to ask questions so you might want to
think about with which questions to ask
so you have something to ask once we're
there so the session topic today is
about a book adrenaline junkies
and template zombies that has been
written by Tom DeMarco and Peter ooshka
and a couple of other guys who are not
here today and well I'm sure you know
both of them they're both members of the
Atlantic System skilled written a couple
of books mostly on well not so much
technical stuff more about the
organizational stuff in projects and in
software and that's what we are going to
talk about today so welcome thank you
Marcus thank you Marcus
so well I already mentioned the book and
I've shown it around brides and I'll put
it into the show notes for you guys
listening so the book is on behavior
patterns right and this is a very
provocative title template zombies
junkies and stuff so what is it what is
it about first of all for those of you
are listening by a podcast year I'm Tom
DeMarco just so you identify the voice
in that and I'm Peter Burke oh yeah
yes the the book is about patterns of
social behavior social interaction so we
chose we chose to write about originally
a hundred and fifty different patterns
that we identified and we ended up with
86 that we thought were good enough ie
general enough to present to to the to
our audience and of these we chose two
of them to be represented in the title
we sort of percent pretended we were
going to have an alphabetic presentation
of the patterns so adrenaline was at the
beginning and zombies at the very end
adrenaline I'll start with the first one
the adrenaline junkies pattern is you
know it well because your organization
very very likely as its familiar its
familiar to you because it's the
organization where you're not really
entirely safe unless you are over busy
unless you unless you're acting as
though your pants were on fire
that's an adrenaline junkie someone who
is at least acting as though his pants
are on fire and temperate zombies is
template zombies is another kind of
person in the project and they're those
persons that believe that you can save a
project by filling in templates and
templates only so you have templates for
everything and a successful project is
one where all the templates are filled
in you should have seen such
organizations that believe in a totally
template driven approach in there and so
we made them the template zombies not
that we dislike templates templates is a
good thing but you can exaggerate peter
has a new template for architecture so
he's not opposed to templates so this
sounds like very negative stuff in the
sense that it's stuff you shouldn't do
right so anti-patterns so it's the book
only about these negative things or is
there also positive behaviors you've
identified well we certainly have We
certainly have some of each the the
negative patterns are frankly more
amusing and so we continually struggled
with ourselves to limit the number of
negative patterns but we have we have
succeeded in in ending up with patterns
that are many negative almost the same
number are positive and there are some
that really are just observations they
are we don't offer a guess as to whether
they're positive or negative
he was surprising but as Tom already
said here the positive patterns are not
so exciting
you see positive behavior and you take
it for granted yes that's the way we
should do it and yes that's what
everybody is doing in there the negative
ones are the ones where you discover
yourself in a mirror say yeah we're
doing such things we know we shouldn't
be doing such things but nevertheless we
do it and so we have about it was
surprising we had about 50% positive and
50% negative patterns in there without
counting first so we simply came up with
observations and yes we do have good
observations in the last 30 years of IT
there is positive things out there if
you find yourself laughing over and we
try to make these interesting and
amusing if you find yourself laughing
over one of the patterns it's almost
certainly a negative pattern and this is
this is the fact that negative things
are more amusing than positive is not
unique to IT or to social organisations
I'm teaching a course this year at the
University of Maine in ethics and the
subject of ethics also finds the
negatives more amusing than the
positives for instance the Norwegian
philosopher Kierkegaard wrote a very
famous book called either/or which is a
dialogue between a sensualist and an
ethical person and even though he was
trying to trying to make the ethical
points that the ethical person gives the
fact of the matter is it's the other guy
that's much more interesting and today
the book is called either/or and either
is the sensual ists part of the dialogue
and or is the ethicists response and
today people don't even read or they
only read either it's funny when I read
the book
in some cases I really couldn't tell and
I wasn't sure what that says about me
yeah I should so that's really
interesting
so why did you write the book what was
the motivation behind it when we started
out working together many years ago
were a bunch of trainers and consultants
traveling around the world in there and
the only thing that held us together was
our experience and so we even made that
our slogan in one of our first ads in
there the experience is our only product
because we had no products we had
nothing else to sell out there but over
the years the gilt always had the
feeling we should create something
together and when we have our yearly
meetings here we were always discussing
such issues we had no idea what that
product would be when we were dreaming
about audio tapes or video files and web
pages and many many other things well we
finally came up with a classic again and
we wrote a book it's the easiest form
that doesn't mean that we might not
present that in different forms in there
but we want it to have something that
joins us together and that somehow
captures the experience that we all made
I think also we wanted the experience of
doing it I feel very emotional about the
experience of working with five
co-authors now if you know people that
write you probably know at least one
person who's been part of a two-person
team who destroyed a friendship in the
process of creating a book and we so
people look at us and say you really had
six co-authors and you really did write
all the patterns together not just
divide them up in one person write one
and other somebody else write another we
worked very closely on these and it was
a a wonderful experience in which we
abused each other terribly but somehow
managed to enjoy it enormous Lee at the
same time
book is also probably very necessary in
the sense that I haven't seen these
kinds of things in other books in that
distilled form so it's not just it's not
just to have a product it's also really
useful for people to read so it's a
really good product and that's and it's
very enjoying to read also there is a
chapter in there from the cutting room
floor so we have many many more patterns
that didn't make it through that quality
process its we had one key also we had a
second potentially a third co-author for
each chapter in there and it had to go
through all the six of us before it got
into the book and as Tom already
mentioned this was a process that wasn't
easy and so a lot of them fell out of
the book and didn't even make it into
the last shortlisted where we have an
interaction method that we used within
the guild and it's called the end way
shout down you shout the other person
down and hey but it fortunately doesn't
it worked out fairly evenly we're all
about equal shoulders I think so you
mentioned before that you as the guild
have this thing that you have this
experience and that's obviously the
stuff that went to the book so from
which project for which kinds of
projects which domains you know how long
how many projects where did you get the
experiments from whether you kind of
mined the patterns from well you have to
know the guilt that this is really a
very distributed organization we only
see each other at most one week a year
otherwise we're all working in different
domains different application areas with
different kinds of projects we have our
specialties in there for instance our
British colleagues Susannah James
Roberts and they are mostly in
requirements engineering and they do
requirements projects all over the world
some research projects in there they
work a lot in Australia with companies
that work all over Europe and in the
u.s. Steve McManaman is more on the
management side he's running startup
team startup companies he's creating new
products in there so his knowledge comes
from building products and shipping them
that I'm more in the architecture
business Tom and Tim you do a lot of
different things different things yeah
but the wonderful things people said
we'd love to have you in for a
consultant to me and then they asked
this very embarrassing pleasure what do
you what do you do and I've tried all my
life not to be in any particular niche
so I don't have an answer to that and
the so I get few consulting assignments
but the ones I get are are very
interesting because of course there's
somebody that has a problem that doesn't
land in a niche which makes it amusing
so it's across domains it's across the
world it's it's many different
application areas that we collected them
even the places that we are living so
far apart that we sell them across our
ways and don't step on our toes in there
and from that lot of experience we can
of course compare that was one of the
most important parts during writing the
book did you see that behavior somewhere
else in the world did you find another
project where that showed up in there
and when when it was only the
observation of one and nobody could
confirm that it was immediately off the
table so we have to see that in
different domains extremely amusing
probably also helps to well see the
differences and commonalities between
different cultures over the world
because you often say you know if you if
you work with people from X country then
things are different but I guess most of
that stuff is kind of cross or
international or cross-cultural well
what nobody's saying of course is that
it also helps that we're very old yeah
we have as we say a hundred and eighty
years of experience across the six of us
which makes us very old right yeah well
see that's the benefit you can write be
there yes there it is so there is no
overall structure to the book it doesn't
have you know here is five patterns on
good behavior and isn't that why is that
or is there a hidden structure or we
wanted the book to be a good read where
you would pick it up and you would the
experience of reading it would be
optimized and so we through
thing is at you with a certain sense of
variation we wanted to keep changing
your experience as you read it and the
other more organized approaches we came
up with just didn't make for such an
interesting reading experience in fact
during our writing process we had
several categories in our minds and we
even have them categorized they will be
discussing very long whether we put them
into the book as icons auras and
notations things like that so we were
looking at patterns that simply are
individual behavior in behavior of
single persons in there sometimes
individuals being project managers other
times they've been programmers and so on
we looked at team behavior we looked at
organizational behavior but we also
classify the long to life cycle with
that is there something in project
planning is there something in
requirements is there something in
quality assurance so we had several
categories and then the end decided to
skip them leave them out and just
present these stories for maximum of
reading pleasure and not categorized by
many many such overall categories but in
fact if you look at these patterns in
there in all of these categories we
found positive behavior and negative
behavior and sometimes observations so
it's not surprising that we deal a lot
with corporate culture that this is one
of the key issues in there and there is
at least six or seven patterns that are
positive in corporate culture and
there's many more that are negative in
this area people are laughing so they
noticed that there is no positive stuff
and the methods and tools well there's
only two in the book in this area on
methods and tools so we didn't
concentrate on that too much maybe
that's okay okay so those of you who by
the way who has read the book
thank you you see the others are an
opportunity to you probably read other
patterns books and you probably noticed
that the
patterns in this book aren't you know
they don't look very much like patterns
there isn't a strict forum I tend to
like this it reads more like a story but
is there any specific reason if I did
that or how come well I just work is I I
like somewhat disagree with your with
your point we we didn't we didn't take
as our template we wouldn't act like
template zombies
we didn't take as our template the book
by the Gang of Four on on software
patterns for example but we did look
very carefully at Christopher
Alexander's original book called a
pattern language and we noticed for
instance that he had three things for
every pattern he had four things
actually a name a picture that
represented an iconic picture a picture
that was iconic of the of the pattern a
pattern description and an essay so at
least in in in one sense we followed
Alexander's approach and it was
interesting it forced us for instance to
have a picture and it forced us to give
a lot of thought to the name of the
pattern and to the to the very short
description of the pattern in fact we
kept telling ourselves this is our book
it's interesting that the book is the
table of contents in a way it's the
names of the patterns now we introduced
some other elements as well we even had
a quality checking thing in there while
writing was that if anybody sees that
structure while reading we failed so you
shouldn't recognize that structure it is
there and we wanted to hide it in the
end to write an essay with all the
elements in there that would be if we
had headlines put in between but we try
to avoid the headlines in between yeah
and makes it much easier to read than
the very strictly structured pattern
through sometimes see and it fits well
this kind of soft topic
okay so one thing you already alluded to
before is that the book contains
observations
it doesn't say do this to this to that
to solve the problem why well first of
all some of the problems are frankly
unsolvable that recognizing them
recognizing your weakness differences
I'm short I will forever be short and
fortunately I recognize it and I don't
date tall girls not date anyone I'm
married but but so recognizing yourself
is important but while the patterns may
be somewhat general the solutions are
not so solving the problem within your
organization we felt that the best thing
we could do is to give you a handle for
the pattern a way to address it a way to
name it a way to describe it so why we
spend so much time on the names of the
patterns many of them went through the
naming process a dozen times I think we
went through the whole we kept going
back over and over on the names and
coming up with a better name well Peter
will show you one pattern a little bit
later where we have actually the
genealogy of the names and we can tell
you a little bit about that but we had
the feeling that if we're successful
that we somebody would be sitting in a
meeting and the the the organizer of the
meeting would make a presentation to
everybody else and somebody would say
sounds like template junkies to me or
even that's number 43 if people have
been reading the book even the numbers
could could become relevant so what's
the pattern with a number 42 I do run an
interesting experiment when I'm teaching
seminars about that book in there
because presenting a pattern I always
ask a question and if you observe it
what would you do about it and it's
really interesting to listen to the
answers that are coming up how many fold
they are and have good ideas and the
interesting thing is there are always
answers coming up there is nobody this
has
I have no idea how I would to react to
that immediately you have a couple of
reactions in the audience and they go
different ways and so we think once you
recognize a pattern you are smart enough
to find out what to do about it but you
have to give it a name you have to bring
it out into the open and then it's easy
sometimes to find a solution sometimes
it's very very hard we have a couple of
patterns there is no strict answer to
that ok so then of course the next
question is is it arty specific I mean
if you think about things like
adrenaline junkie I guess that's not
necessarily restricted to software
products our experience base is very
largely from the IT industry so much of
the many of the observations come from
that industry we're always amazed to
find that people from other industries
are picking the book up for instance
nurses we I had some feedback from group
of nurses teams of nurses that have been
reading the book and found some value in
it so it isn't entirely I speak IT
specific but it is specific to domains
where people are knowledge workers and
where they interact in groups where they
it's not just individual experience but
it's group experience we recently
received an email from a family
therapist in New Zealand telling us that
about 60% of our patterns are applicable
to her day to day work and we did never
plan to make a book for family
therapists so this was not our target
audience in there so since our
experience comes from Mikey it also
maybe opens up a new you know ways to
earn money for family therapists they
could go into software projects and how
about so we've had this meta discussion
about the book for long enough now I
think we should look at some of the
specific patterns to give people and the
listening audience an idea about some of
the you know examples and some of some
concrete stuff so why don't you show us
tell us about a couple of your favorite
ones I was thinking before I went with
this just questions here what to pick
and in terms of worldwide financial
crisis
we picked two examples that we want to
show you and the first one is one that
we called short pencil the the titled
short pencil comes from the observation
made by one of Tim Lister's clients that
he hates working for a company where you
have to turn in a short pencil before
they'll give you a long one back the
cost controls are so strong that that
you have to look out for every penny we
want to we're trying to build quality
products and the idea of living in non
quality life while you're building a
quality product seems like a terrible
contradiction so we observe that in some
companies they've had successive waves
of cost reduction that began to
interfere with the organization's
ability to get work done they've become
so focused on cost that they've lost
track of why they're there cost
reduction can seem like the business
you're in and if it does seem like the
business you're in something is terribly
wrong you again ask the questions what
would you do if you live in such a
company where you have to turn in a
short pencil in order to get a long one
and one of my participants came up with
a fantastic answer take the long pencil
break it into four parts return them and
you'll find for the next period in there
so you think we are clever enough to
overcome that if the company tries to
put such limits on us in there there's
always people who find ways to live with
that and together or it and their
companies that are over an extended
period of time really are in the
business of reducing their own costs are
are in a state that in a human being you
would call bulimia they are they're
becoming anorexic and that is fatal it
is fatal to the company in the long run
and to your career in the short run so
if it's if it's serious enough if your
company is seriously enough and
enough involved in cost reduction then
you really probably should be looking to
be someplace else because it's not good
for you may be good for it but not good
for you before we look at the next
pattern you should stop harming yourself
right you should stop asking questions
very soon here are some microphones so
if you have questions you might want to
start you know thinking about how to
work them I picked another one that is
mostly true in terms of crisis in there
we do observe that there is no backup
for project teams if somebody drops out
somebody is sick or so there's nobody to
do the work in there and we call that no
bench a pattern that definitely the
varium unique doesn't know because they
keep the world best soccer player on the
bench and don't even let them out on the
field in there they can afford to buy
the most expensive players and not to
let them play but think about your
project is there somebody on the bench
is there somebody that can jump in if
something happens in the project and we
find a lot of companies where the bench
is totally empty speaking in theater
terms not even under studies there that
can take the role and nobody really
qualified to jump in there it's a very
very dangerous patterns if your filter
that your bench is total totally empty
well it's not dangerous if everything
goes well but if anything goes wrong
lucky lose someone redundancy is the
ultimate risk management tool a little
bit of redundancy I mean think about if
you have to be in in New York for a
meeting Wednesday morning you could
conceivably leave fairly late on Tuesday
and maybe make it if you got to the
airport on time and if your flight was
on time and if the taxi went fast enough
you could probably get to the meeting
but if the taxi was slow or there's too
much traffic and you're complaining to
the taxi driver we'll come on I need to
be there
you're acting like many IT organizations
when in fact what they should have done
was believe the day earlier and and and
be there a whole day and spend the
afternoon shopping in New York and go
you know sleep overnight in a nice hotel
and go on time to the meeting the next
morning in other words you leave
yourself a little cushion of something
well we're trying particularly in the IT
business and particularly in this
economic climate
we're so optimized we're trying to do
everything without any reserve at all
and that almost always means that we end
up doing things much more slowly than we
could have because we have no reserve to
count on when inevitably something goes
wrong of course having that reserve is
expensive so what do you do with the
people on the bench while they're not
primary you know players well they can
be secondary players they can there's
always work to do they can do extra work
but the key thing is they're
overqualified for what they're do you
have some people that are overqualified
but they also understand that they are
serving the role of understudy now why
does an understudy accept the role of
understudy it's because of the
possibility of the moment of glory and
they are actually up on the stage
okay now it's your turn I knew that
would happen
yeah Linda go ahead I thanks for being
here you guys this is great I have two
comments and a question is that Alright
okay
first comment I'm really happy to see
this book because I love patterns and a
lot of people in this room might not
know that an early version of people
where one of a great number of books
from the Atlantic systems guild that's
made a tremendous impact on software
development
was among the first published sources
inside software to mention Christopher
Alexander there's a whole chapter there
on Christopher Alexander's patterns so
something I didn't realize until just
recently when I went back to look at
people where ii comment a lot of the
exercises that we do in retrospectives
come from family therapy and are
applicable to teams in software
development interesting the question I
know that your patterns are different
from a lot of other patterns but the
goal has always been in writing patterns
to produce a pattern language so that
people who were interested in that
domain could speak in that language now
it sounds like that is happening do you
notice that that's happening both within
your group and your teaching classes so
that the people who come out of your
classes begin to speak these patterns
certainly in the current the
correspondence that we receive people
are speaking in this in these terms but
of course that's they're speaking to us
I have now I have had the experience
with people aware of sitting next to
somebody on an airplane with reading
people where I've never had that
experience with this book yet but I
think
I have great hopes that it will become
exactly that that was our goal as to
whether it will actually happen the book
is fairly new it's been out a year and
it's I think it will have a long life
because we're we're dealing with matter
ins matters that don't change from day
to day they are the relatively constants
of our our experience and they will be
the same for a generation behind us I
believe so I expect it I hope that that
will happen Linda your comment about
Christopher Alexander in all fairness
the reason so many of us in the IT field
are aware of patterns and are aware of
Alexander's contribution comes from one
man and that was Eddie Jordan Edie Orton
very early on in the early 70s was
holding up a copy of not just a pattern
language but also notes on the synthesis
of form by Christopher Alexander and
saying this is it this is the book this
is the holy book that we need to pattern
our behavior upon our actions our
techniques and our designs and so I a
personal debt to Eddie Jordan from the
early 1970s for making a very strong
statement that forced all of us and
rippled through the IT industry but came
from one person and that was Ed York did
the kind the plain talk to you then
did he notice well I did introduce
myself next question okay first of all I
didn't read the book yet so maybe you've
wrote about exactly that already but I
was wondering when creating the book did
you notice that there's some clustering
between the patterns in the sense that
if a company is suffering from let's say
Shaw pencil it's most likely also
suffering from low bench so that when I
sought one pattern I might be interested
in checking whether other related
patterns apply as well
not really I would say we tried to more
or less make sure that each pattern is
found in multiple places in the world
but we did not cross check whether these
companies suffer from other bad behavior
or they enjoy other good behavior in
there so I could not confirm that in
what I have clusterings Peter I disagree
a little bit in that when we when we
looked back over what we started to tell
stories to each other that particularly
for the bad patterns the same companies
were involved in many of the stories you
know I so that does suggest a certain
clustering of bad patterns and it would
probably be an interesting study it
would be an interesting study in there
yes I agree the same names came up all
the time in there but we never mapped it
down to the individual pattern level
whether whether you could really see an
influence if one does that it does also
to the other things in there it would be
very interesting study well while we're
waiting for somebody else to please
please leap in and give your comments or
your questions I'd be interested more in
your comments than your questions for
instance what patterns are you seeing
and what name would you give to them
what is a pattern of your organization
that that you feel needs a name and you
might share it with somebody else we're
always interested in that work we are a
collection service for other people's
patterns but I would mention something
about the experience of writing in the
book as I said it was a very emotional
experience it was one in which we found
our friendships getting closer and
closer
I now I've had a wonderful co-author
experience with Tim Lister before he's a
wonderful co-author and I a lot about
his style and in particular his writing
style Tim his original draft of anything
I don't care what it is his original
draft is only about half as long is
about to be the ideas are so thickly
clustered in Tim's writing
the wonderful ideas even the jokes are
so thickly clustered that in reading it
through at the normal reading speed you
miss half of them and so I would say
just him you need to slow it down to him
you need to to give the person's mind a
chance to catch up and he said how do
you slow down writing and I would say
what you put in Phil you put in
meaningless intervals of writing in
between the meaningful ones and he said
are you serious and I said yes now watch
I'll do this and I would take one of his
patterns one of his essays and I would
interject meaningless commentary
meaningless to give the mind a chance to
catch up and he would look at it he'd
say okay I agree it is better it is
better so here I'm an experience of
adding meaningless stuff to somebody
else's writing and he is such a
beautiful human being that he could put
up with that and even see the value of
it it was a was a very enjoyable
experience working with not just working
with the group of six but working with
each individual as we we worked in pairs
for part of the process and we paired up
so everybody got to work with everybody
else and all of those experience I had
experiences I treasure I was exercising
at my local gymnasium one day and I was
on a treadmill next to a woman who's a
thermos
and she she asked me what I did and I
said I'm a writer and then I said you
know I'm I'm a writer but I haven't
written anything for almost a year said
why is that and I said well you know I
did this project and it finished last
January and I've just never been able to
pick up another writing project since
then she said well tell me a little bit
about the writing project you just
finished I said oh there were six of us
co-authors and we interacted in this way
and that way and she said I know why you
haven't been able to write since then
it's because you're going back to
writing as a lonely
individual business and it's just not
the same and she's right it's not the
same hello my name is Elizabeth and
thank you very much for writing this
book it seems to me that I definitely
have to read it so you were asking for
comments I'm working with insights MDI
types or type well kind of types to see
how people react how they influence a
project are they more the adrenaline
junkies fighting for their rights or
they are the leaders keeping everything
together and say ok we do it that way we
do it that way and there are 60 types of
people of individual behavior and so I
can help people bridging the gaps within
the bro check its another time thank you
so much there are Elizabeth you're
saying there are 60 different
identifiable types of individual
behavior active in the workplace I never
heard that exact idea but I don't doubt
that that's true did you give them a
name each one has a name eight of them
have a name and the other ones have
combinations of colors of different
colors for example we have a 60% part of
the leader part it's the red one and you
have a 20% part of the yellow one a it's
the action the adrenaline junkie yeah
and the other one I don't know maybe the
blue one that's the template freak and
so you can mix them up eight of them
have a real name and the other ones more
for the psychologists to interpret the
book goes a little bit above the
classification of persons only we have
identified behavior that is not person
specific this belongs to a certain phase
in the project or a certain activity in
a project in there so yes the two title
patterns are personal specific but
there's a lot of other PAPR in there
that is not person specific it belongs
the whole team it belongs to the overall
organization okay thank you very much so
is there a relationship to you know
things like the disc profile you know
you know these things like where people
are classified you know she said
myers-briggs
you see this is kind of in the same you
know kind of area is it you know yeah
understanding these characteristics of
personalities in various ways is of
course a way to expect certain behavior
from those people in there and so it is
along the same lines yes well it is one
of the things that other classification
schemes from psychology I have as a
characteristic is they come to you along
with the person who is determined to
push you into a pattern and our approach
has been entirely different we have
where we have no inclination to push you
into a pattern to say you must be this
or that rather we're just offering the
patterns for you if you recognize them
then if you recognize yourself in one of
these patters or your organization in
one of these patterns then the pattern
is going to be useful to you and if you
don't you'll just roll your eyes and say
imagine working for a company where this
was true I mean how crazy it won't make
any sense to you at all there are no
more questions than I would suggest we
look at two more patterns and then we
wrap it up okay well let's see let me
take the pattern there is no crying in
baseball
it comes from a comes from a film that
you may have seen called a league of
their own about a women's baseball
league that has a male manager who when
one of the players begins to cry because
he's abused her he says there's no
crying in baseball I mean you're not
supposed to cry and we've noticed that
I've noticed that certainly in my own
interaction if somebody begins to become
too emotional there's almost immediately
going to be someone that will say you
know that's not professional right to
show that a much emotion is not
professional and
that sends a message that caring deeply
about things is not emotional well that
message is a very negative message
because we want people to care
desperately about the things they're
doing and I think while we're at it it's
also a very anti-female message it's no
surprise that that woman's tears are
closer to the surface than men's are and
so we're sort of saying it's not
entirely professional to be a woman and
I know that that idea is one that many
of us have felt very comfortable with
because we grew up with that in an
environment where that seemed to be
prevailing wisdom but we need to work we
need to move beyond it particularly
going to feel like IT which depends for
its lifeblood life's blood on the very
agile and active and useful contribution
of our women participants so the idea
that there is no crying in baseball that
the crying that extremely displays of
emotion are somehow anti professional
simply operates against the best
interest of your organization if you
recognize that pattern in yourself you
need to correct it because it's the
people that get that can get very
emotional that are bound to be major
contributors but I warn you in advance
they are a pain to deal with
I mean don't expect it to be entirely
easy to deal with people's emotions one
more one more now we have three minutes
we have two five minutes we have a
couple of parents in there where the
title is really cryptic and it's not
easy to explain what we are talking
about so for instance we are teaching
the world even in our English version of
the book a new German word in there
which is sealant for lunch after so you
find that title in the English book and
you find it of course also in the German
book in there and maybe this is
something for the opie conference here
since you hear a lot about extreme
programming here and then about their
child teams and so on here and we found
organizations that really have tea
in their sailing event the teams in
there that really ignore every rule of
the company but they are very successful
and they throw out software and software
they are not extreme programmers because
as you know extreme programming is a
very strict disappointment you have to
follow a lot of rules in there
but these teams they simply they work by
sitting together and throwing out
software it's sort of guerilla teams in
there so if you have such Karelia teams
let them be
let them do good work in there of course
you cannot put them on the productizing
of something and the Quality Assurance
and writing user documentation so please
use such teams in an early phase when
you want to be innovative when you need
two prototypes in there and the other
observation is you can't form such teams
they either exist or they don't exist
and it's not easy to enter such a team
because they have very very high
internal quality standards but that has
nothing to do with quality standards of
your company in there they wouldn't
accept any member that doesn't fulfill
the same kind of quality standards the
team has and so these are again teams
you can't manage but if you have them
use them for the best you excluded
extreme programming but think about the
people who invented extreme programming
camp back in his group when they were
first conceiving of of extreme
programming they were they say linear
Avant team I mean there was no no other
way to see it and in this pattern and
guess this is something to wrap it up
there we came up with a nice pun at the
end yeah if you have such a team in
there if you bet you're go a thing on
such a team make sure you get che
guevara and not jelly you know the
German version of the American version
of Howard Schmidt of course so so it's
this project finished are you continuing
to collect patterns or is there a you
know Burton - I think what we're looking
at now is the possibility of building a
book of organizational patterns that
would be explicitly steered
out beyond the world of IT and would not
have any individual patterns in it but
would be organizational thousand just
because we we so enjoyed the process of
working together we want to turn it
around to you in there if you read those
patterns sure you find some that that
apply to your organization some of the
good ones hopefully and not only the bad
ones in there send us your patterns give
us your observations in there try to
give them names bring them out into the
open and there we we act as a collector
for you and we might include them in
future versions we definitely keep on
collecting ourselves in there but we
have no plans at the moment to publish
in your book okay then
Tom Peter thank you Marcus thank you
thank you Marcus and thanks for asking
questions and stuff
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SE radio team via
the website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at s e - radio net or if
it is specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
Creative Commons 2.5 licence please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the positive music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]